為什麼是不合格呢?
不合格的拯救者是一位我們很熟悉的、很出名的
或者是聲名狼藉的一個士師
他的名字叫做「參算」
我們會看四章聖經
我想其實四章聖經你不可能三十分鐘內讀完或看完
我們也要慢慢地分析
去看為什麼我們會給這個題目「不合格的拯救者」
今年年初二月的時候
我不知道大家是否喜歡看電影
有一齣電影叫做「參算」
有沒有人看過?
不太多人看
因為那齣電影是兒童不宜的
叫做PG-13
其實真正在聖經裡記載的應該是Rater R或者Rater M才對
但它已經是Rater PG-13
但是變成了一齣可以說是不太成功的電影
我不敢說是票房毒藥
但是如果你看影評
Rotten Tomato 全都是一顆星
五顆裡面只有一顆
為什麼呢?
其實真的很難
你要將聖經裡面這四章聖經關於參算的事蹟
真的如原本般血淋淋地拍成電影
那你一定是Rater R
但是你又要多說一些聖經裡面的真理
兩個東西都拉不起來
所以一出了是PG-13就慘了
家長又不能帶小孩去看
因為是兒童不宜的
要13歲以上才可以去
大人如果不是基督徒
PG-13是沒東西看的
又不想去看
結果就不是很受得了
但是在教會的層面
當我們看參算的時候
就很不同了
我們通常教小朋友參算
就講到他很可愛
參算是一個大力士
為上帝去征戰
為了不要讀完四章聖經
我只用三分鐘來做一個簡單的總結
我就找了天主教字幕版的卡通片給你們看
如果你們真的不認識參算的故事
我們就看看這次的字幕版
參算的簡單和聖潔的兒童故事是怎樣的
我們來看看
One of the leaders of God's people
was chosen before he was born
An angel told the mother
You will have a son
but you must never cut his hair
His long hair will show that he's a Nazarite
someone who has work to do for God
This baby grew up to be very strong
His name was Samson
and he always won against his enemies
Samson had a friend named Delilah
She asked
What makes you so strong, Samson?
At first, he wouldn't tell her
She begged and whined
Finally, he said
If someone shaved my head, I would lose my strength
When Samson fell asleep
Delilah had someone shave off his hair
Samson wasn't strong anymore
Now his enemies had no trouble taking him to their prison
In prison, Samson's hair grew long again
One night, his enemies had a party
They brought Samson in and made fun of him
Samson prayed
Lord, please, give me strength one more time
And God did
When Samson pushed against the pillars
that held up the building
Down it all came on top of everyone
Those people would never hurt anyone again
In this cartoon, we can see that Samson and Delilah had a friend named Delilah
We know that Samson didn't lose his strength because of his long hair
It's because Delilah's spirit left him
So he lost his ability to do great deeds
Pastor Alan finally realized something
If you don't have long hair, you have strength
In the end, Samson lost his hair
Now it's PJ's turn
Don't have long hair
It's because God gave Samson strength
But if we look at Samson's story
Many people in the world today dream of a strong leader
One man can kill a lot of people
He can defeat an entire army
For example, Rambo, Dirty Harry, Keenan Eastwood, Die Hard, John McClane
One man can defeat an entire army
In this day and age, there are not many people who can do that
Nowadays, there are Jason Bourne, Kingsman, Iron Man, Batman
One man can defeat an entire army
These are the heroes and leaders that modern people have never seen
It should be like that
But the Samson mentioned in the Bible
is contrary to many values of Christianity
So many Christians have a contradiction
Why did God choose Samson to be a priest?
And Samson is listed as one of the heroes in the 11th chapter of Hebrews
Why?
We need to understand that God did not choose a perfect man
God chose a man with a perfect heart
But if we look at Samson's life
We can't see much of his spiritual appearance
So many people say that God put these four chapters in the Bible
In so many verses, God used the most number of chapters to describe what he did wrong
This is also appreciated by the authors in the Bible
The Bible does not hide the mistakes of many spiritual leaders
Whether it's David, Abraham, Samson, Jehovah, or Gideon
God has shown us that we don't need a perfect man
We need God's mercy to give us this opportunity to serve
On the other hand, we need to understand why today's topic is called "Inappropriate"
Since God used Samson, what is "Inappropriate"?
In the eyes of people, he is absolutely inappropriate
He killed an entire army by himself
He turned the world upside down
But did he accomplish God's mission?
Let's take a look at the whole story
And let's see what we can learn from it today
Let's take a look at the 13th chapter of the Bible
At the beginning of the first chapter, God began to describe this event
The Israelites walked again, and they saw evil in their eyes
God said, "Put them in the hands of the Philistines for forty years."
God raised up the Philistines
The Philistines were about 1150 BC
They were a group of people on the Greek peninsula
They were driven to Egypt because of the defeat
They were exiled to Egypt by Ramses III, a pharaoh
Then they went from Jerusalem to the place of Gaza today
They settled in these five cities
The blood came from there, and they began to conflict with the Israelites
Until David and Solomon settled the Philistines
Until the Roman Empire ruled the land of Israel
They named this place "Palestine"
In fact, "Palestine" is the land of the Philistines
The land of the Philistines
In fact, the Romans were very clever
They deliberately used the name "Palestine" to humiliate the Israelites
If you don't have your own land, you don't have your own country
Now this country belongs to the Philistines
So this is how "Palestine" came to be
Until today
So people often debate whether it was the Palestinians or the Israelites who came first
In fact, it was only God who came first
But this is what they are facing
But it is very strange that this is also an act of righteousness and evil in the eyes
We look at this circle of the city
We have seen this picture
The whole circle is a circle of the city
This is the sixth circle
There are more than ten cities that have not recorded this circle
But the circle has a very special feature
They do not recognize God
They leave God in a bad way
Then God handed them over to the Arabs
And they were oppressed
Then the Israelites pleaded
Then they asked God for forgiveness
And they went back to God
But there are two very special things recorded here
The first thing is
In the sixth circle
The previous five circles have always been like this
The sixth circle
Did not mention the Israelites
The Israelites have pleaded God
But the special thing is
Forty years is the longest time recorded in the historical records
These people are oppressing the Israelites
The longest time is forty years
Forty years is basically two generations
There are already two generations
The first generation may have died
They have been oppressed for such a long time
And people have not pleaded God
So some scholars say
In fact, most of the Israelites had left Jehovah
So they did not know who Jehovah was
The second thing is
Some people may no longer care
Whether they can get out of the oppression
Because they are already used to it
Forty years
From birth to the age of forty
They have become slaves
I have become a slave
They are already used to such a thing
This time, we will be in the world
It is not that we are also facing this kind of flood
God wants us to shine and shine in the world of chaos
But sometimes we are already used to it
Everyone does this
The world is getting worse and worse
There is nothing we can do
The people who believe in Jesus are getting lower and lower
Or we are getting lower and lower
There is no way to face this flood
We will definitely fall
It is difficult to do this
So in the past many years
I have met a very famous witness
Developed these five things
Let's take a look
A qualified savior
Or a qualified leader
A qualified Christian
Every Christian is a leader
There are five things I call 5D
In our Christian life
We must have
In order to be able to fulfill the mission God has given us
In the eyes of people, Jesus is definitely a qualified leader
But in the eyes of God
And in reality
He has been a priest for twenty years
He did not help the Israelis
To get rid of the Philistines
That's right, he killed a lot of Philistines
But he did not fulfill the mission God gave him
Isn't this what many Christians are embarrassed about today?
I have been a Christian for twenty years
But I have never preached the gospel
I have never led anyone to believe in God
Isn't this what we are embarrassed about?
So this famous witness developed these five things
Let's take a look at these five things
Let's see if there are any of these things
And when I want to listen to your sermon
Let's see if there are any of these five things
This famous witness is called Leung Ting-Ik
Let's see what these five things are
The first thing I call 5D
In our Christian life
Devotion is your spirituality
Are you building a personal relationship with God every day?
You ask yourself
The second thing is discipline
Your discipline
These disciplines are the discipline of the Holy Spirit
Are you constantly practicing some kind of practice for your spiritual growth?
These practices include your spiritual cultivation, your reading the Bible, your own vision
Some people even starve, some people retire, etc.
The third thing is direction
Do you live your life for the mission of God?
Have you realized that God wants us to live a mission?
Where is your direction?
Many Christians today still have no direction
The fourth thing is discipleship
Do you have the heart of a disciple?
Are you willing to pass on what you have learned to others?
Brothers and sisters, this is very important
In the 20th chapter of Jesus Christ's Great Mission
In the 28th chapter of Jesus Christ's Great Mission
In the 19th chapter of Jesus Christ's Great Mission
It is mentioned last time
We have to bring people to the Lord in the name of the Holy Spirit
In the 20th chapter of Jesus Christ's Great Mission
No one is going to read it
The 20th chapter of Jesus Christ's Great Mission
能夠完成上帝的使命
次下這個小朋友出來的時候
要他高納他們做拿西爾人
我們先說一下拿西爾人是什麼
除了這樣之外
又次他一個很獨特的天生神力
嘩 厲害
一個人可以打死一千人
還有他一路成長
爸爸媽媽都很愛惜他
很遷就他
他也有上帝一路給他的經驗
去安納他做時事
給他機會去做領袖
完成上帝的使命
看到這些的時候
我經常都想到
我們基督徒豈不是都是這樣呢
我們每一個其實都是天之驕子
今天得了這個救恩
也在一個自由社會裏去信耶穌
我們有很多的所謂的知識
很多的資源給了我們
但是我們和上帝的關係是怎樣
有時候教會
我覺得很多時候人們誤會
我來自一間不斷增長的教會
在香港
很多人誤會教會就是
大 增長 棒棒聲
但是屬靈一定很差
我們每一個做牧者
都不會告訴你
我們不斷增長
但是靈不靈你也不用理
但是我們希望頂尖會明白
我們不斷增長的時候
教會越做越大
但是我們必須要越做越深
我們必須要維持我們全間教會
個別頂尖會和上帝的關係
這次參宣有沒有在這方面做得到呢
四章聖經裏面
記載了兩次參宣的祈禱
這兩次的祈禱都是參宣
面對他自己的神力
沒有辦法幫他解決問題的時候
他才去找上帝
所以這個我們叫做臨急抱佛腳
臨急抱主腳
第一次是什麼呢
參宣非常口渴
無論多大力都好
力者不能自救
勇士不能自舉其身
沒有辦法幫自己解決口渴的問題
大力都沒有用
於是他祈禱求耶和華
然後聖經怎樣記載呢
耶和華給他水喝
然後在菲律賓人管轄的時候
參宣作以色列的事事
二十年
大家記住
然後下一句
就是他臨死的時候
抱著他的柱子
把菲律賓人殺死
聖經記載他又向上帝祈禱
主耶和華求你眷念我
上帝就這一切一次求你賜給我力量
參宣第二次的祈禱
聖經又記載
參宣作以色列的事事二十年
你看整本的事事記
唯一是參宣被記載兩次
去做以色列人的事事二十年
你說聖經是不是寫多了
不是
是作者故意告訴你
每一次聖經的作者提這句話
參宣作以色列的事事二十年
都是參宣向上帝祈禱之後記載
這件事提醒我們每一個基督徒
很重要的一件事
上帝看重你
不是因為你做得多大做得多多
是你願意回到上帝面前
告訴上帝
爸爸,我不行,我需要你
是你不但認識這位上帝
你更加要找他幫你
聖經的作者不會無緣無故說這些
也不會無緣無故說到
參宣當求告上帝的時候
上帝就告訴所有讀者知道
他是我選擇的,因為他還認得我
可惜這不是持續的關係
今天很多基督徒
我經常跟這些讀者說
我們的上帝太小
我們把上帝只放在教堂裡
放在小組裡,放在茶經裡
只要我們生活上太少部分
所以我們的上帝太弱,太小
因為我們上帝無法影響我們踏出教會之後
去喝茶的時候,或者明天上班的時候
我們跟子女和夫婦聊天的時候
我們上帝無法影響我們
但一到臨急抱主腳的時候
我們就會找上帝
我想問問大家,自己做一下評估
究竟你跟上帝的關係是怎樣
第二件事,我們看看紀律
你是不是贏在起跑線
各位家長,我來香港經常都聽到一句話
贏在起跑線
參選贏了,起跑線
但是,他衝不到終點
輸在終點線有什麼用呢
你要贏在起跑線,你就要下苦功
這就叫做屬靈的紀律
上帝給了他三個紀律
所以,屬靈的紀律就是提醒某些東西
當你不斷去做的時候
不是律法,或者不是一些逼你去做的困難
而是有一些意思在當中
這三件事就是第一件事
不可以清酒濃酒都不可
在苗文素記第六章裡面說到
這個拿世爾人的時候
有三件事,清酒濃酒任何葡萄籽的製品
葡萄籽麵包,Raisin,葡萄籽乾
全部都不可以吃
為什麼呢?
因為當時社會很多飲宴都是喝酒的
他希望你脫離世間上的肉念和煩囂
你分別為成
第二件事,不准碰死屍
你還沒講到,你碰了死屍
有很多上帝的祭司又要去潔淨自己
又要搞很多事,又不可以接觸人
所以不要搞這麼多事
盡量不要碰死屍
你會用多點時間侍奉上帝
第三件事,不可以剃頭
不是因為頭髮有力量
而是一個官面
讓人一見到你的樣子
不是流浪漢
他不剃頭,他就是拿世爾人
這是上帝讓他去學習培育的東西
要幫他成為一個好的領袖
記住,屬靈的操練不是救恩的條件
大家都知道參選做領袖
很多不是拿世爾人都被上帝揀選
但上帝偏是希望他能夠用這些東西
去幫他成為一個更加完成上帝使命的領袖
但他怎麼做呢?我們看看聖經
於是他去飲宴
去亭拿道
去葡萄園
去葡萄園幹什麼?叫你不要喝酒
你去葡萄園
接著下一章說到
飲宴七日七夜
飲宴當然是牽涉喝酒
接著下一章說到
他打死一隻獅子
將獅子撕開
然後走回獅子的屍骸
見到有蜜糖
拿來吃
最後說到
有一塊未乾的蘆筛骨
即是那隻小驢死了
但還未腐化,死了不久
他用蘆筛骨打死了一千個菲律斯人
厲害
我計算過
如果用十五秒打死一個人
打死一個人不是那麼容易
我給你十五秒打死一個人
大家知不知道要用多少時間打死一千人
四個小時
你想想他天生神力
很厲害
最後說到他被人剃頭
大利拉的故事不需要多讀
他沒有好好地操練自己
今天我們很多的操練
不會令我們即時死亡
或者失去救恩
舉個例子
刷牙
每天早上我刷牙,晚上我刷牙
你不刷牙你不會即時牙齒消失
或者你不會即時死
或者你不會即時有口腔發炎
或者不會即時
或者你不刷牙一輩子都未必有事
我不知道
第二件事
剛才你們來教會的時候
停下車
將窗戶升高
出車的時候將所有貴重物品拿走
然後鎖好你的車
是不是
你不做這些事,沒有犯法的
沒有人抓你坐牢
為什麼你這樣做
因為這是一個紀律
你學會的紀律就是
教會都是不安全的地方
都會有人break in
因為有外面的人來
所以不好了
我還是把車鎖好
這是保障你自己不會受傷害
你不鎖車
是不是代表你不是一個好基督徒
不是
我又不祈禱,又不讀經
我得了救恩就算了
我一樣侍奉上帝
不會即時死的
但是
你會慢慢慢慢
離開上帝,就好像參宣一樣
參宣也不是即時
是不是,會死的
但是他都是一步步離開上帝
一步步
觸犯了這些屬靈的紀律
所以第二件事要問
弟兄姊妹
究竟在你生命裡面
你有沒有專心去操練
一些屬靈的操練
去幫助你在主裡面成熟
成長
你的靈修
你的讀經
你的對修
這些不會令你即時死的
你不做
但是這些是幫你
屬靈的成長
很重要的東西
第三件事
究竟參宣有沒有做到
上帝要他做的事呢
沒錯
他天生神力
可以撕開的獅子
可以承認記載到
就是那些分裂士人要抓他
他睡覺的時候
分裂士人要抓他
他就走去城門
把整個城門的門框
通常都是鐵做的
拆了出來
然後背著門框
走38里
去到對面的山頂
上面放在那裏
他可以大力到這樣
是不是
很厲害
他做的事是不是
為上帝去做呢
我們看看聖經怎樣說
我們看整個參宣的生命
都是為自己
為自己開心
滿足自己的需要
滿足自己的欲念
參宣怒氣大作
他就走去他爸爸的家
這裡說到
請記載到
參宣對湯姆士說
這次我若加害分裂士人就不算是我的錯
你看下一句
參宣說
這名妓女怎樣做
我必向您報仇才肯罷休
他整個生命就是
我
要滿足我自己
下一句
他就去盧鰓骨
殺了一千人
又是我
最後都是我
他臨死前和上帝祈禱都是
因為他挖我雙眼
我要報仇
又是我
上帝給他的力量是
拓展上帝的使命
完成上帝的使命
但他卻用了
為自己滿足
自己的想要
和需要
這個是不是又值得我們去思想
上下一頂智慧
今天我們
上帝給了很多東西我們
我們有沒有用來
用在上帝的
使命當中
第四樣東西
這個叫滿道訓練
你是不是
有受教的心
有沒有將你所學的東西
教導其他人呢
我叫他做
天下無敵手
來來去去一條友
你沒有用的
給你威風
給你怎樣威風都好
給你威風三十年四十年
你下去一個人
你見到的
全部都是一個人打死一千人
一個人
殺死很多不同的人
沒有用的
他完全沒有
一個受教的心
他見到那個女人他喜歡
見到一個女子
於是
上面稟告父母
中文也比較好
告訴他父母
原文裡面
這個詞好像是一個命令式
和純粹通知
父母
告訴父母我喜歡了一個女孩
請你
讓我娶她為妻
他要這樣做
於是父母跟他說
在會點教會不是有很多美女嗎
為什麼要娶那些
不是信耶穌的人
跟他們拍拖
為什麼要這樣做呢
他不聽勸
我要娶她
因為我喜歡她
那時候我聽國民慈母師
說
參選
年輕人基本上
用這句三字
詞語的說話
對父母說
我覺得不只是年輕人
我們每一個弟兄姊妹
都是這樣
第一句說話
我喜歡
第二句說話
父母可能會問你
你喜歡她什麼
我不知道
你這樣下去
沒有將來
我不在乎
我不管
當你想說下去的時候
他會告訴你
看看怎樣
英文叫
Leave me alone
不要再騷擾我
我喜歡做
你看參選
整個生命都是這樣
人做初一
他做100個初一
去
回報
報復
人家做在他身上
但是更加嚴重
一切都是為
他自己
最後弟兄姊妹
檢查一下自己
究竟你在生命裡面
有沒有一個好的
見證
是不是有一個好的見證
有人看到你是鹽和鋼
這句經文
不需要再講那麼多
因為聖經裡面都講了很多
最出名的這句話
參選去了加薩
也是菲利士人的地方
看到一個妓女就與他親近
上帝揀選的那西爾人
要去拯救
以色列人脫離
菲利士人的手
但是她的生活是微爛不堪
結果她有沒有
做到上帝要她
做到的事呢
是沒有
結尾的時候你看看怎麼寫
這樣參選死的時候
所殺的人比活著
所殺的人更加多
如果有一句說話
形容我們傳道人
我覺得這是一個黑色幽默
聖經作者很搞笑
因為你做了慈師
二十年
上帝要你給你天生神力
要你殺敵
但你死的時候殺的
比你過了二十年殺的加起來更多
那你做了什麼啊
大哥
你試想想有PJ在這裡
找你做個開玩笑
你想想PJ的墓志銘
上面寫著
來PJ喪禮
聚會的人
比他二十年來
在PJ
加起來聽他講道的人更加多
那你還要做什麼
大哥
你做了二十年
一次死的時候
還多人過
二十年加起來的人
你想想上帝呼召
參選做了二十年慈師
他殺過多少敵人
他幫上帝
的工作脫離
菲利士人的手他做了多少
所以我們覺得
他是DQ
不合格
不合格不是因為他特別聖潔
而是他沒有
完成上帝
要他做的事
保羅在
哥倫多前書裡面講
他
要攻克己身
以身服我
你問PJ就知道他以前是做運動員
現在當然不行
以前年輕的時候
每次打死幾隻
做運動員
要攻克己身
如果不是的話
恐怕被欺絕
DQ
不合格
一個沒有上帝恩慈
贏在
起跑線
有上帝給他最好的資源
成長的環境
神賜給他
那麼大的恩慈
他卻沒有用力
完成上帝給他的使命
這是一件很可悲的事
弟兄姊妹
這讓我們每一個
在這五個D裡面
要去看看
究竟我們
今天是贏在起跑線
輸在衝點線
因為我們
到最後的時候
好像保羅所說
當跑那裡
我跑那裡
跑完,左上的道我守住
尾開的帳
我打贏了
參宣打贏
很多場小的帳
但是輸了
整個的戰爭
在今年三月
英國
室內田徑賽
出現了一場
我叫很搞笑的結果
看看這幅圖
新聞形容是室內田徑賽
今年三月
男子400米的初賽
所有人
DQ
一個偷步
另一個踩界,另一個撞人
所有人
史無前例,同組無人生還
全部DQ
有些是跑完才知道的
是帶頭的英國
那個是不知道什麼賽亞軍
在初賽裡面跑贏
到最後DQ
你說多丟臉呢
我都不想我們基督徒
回到上帝面前
上帝說
主啊,我為你做了多少
DQ,不合格
你有沒有完成
上帝要我們完成的
求主幫助我們
求主幫助我們每一個家長
我們香港來的人
我們常聽的贏再起飽膳
我們有沒有關心子女
屬靈的生命
能不能夠
有一天見主面的時候
能夠被主稱讚
是良善
忠心的基督徒
求主幫助我們
我們一起低頭,我們做個禱告
天父我們來到你面前感謝你
因為主我們
不單只需要力量
需要能力,我們更加需要的就是
主在你裡面
我們願意回到你面前說
我們需要你
無論我們教會增長到多大
多多人
我們更加需要的就是
主,我們和你建立一個
持續愛的關係
以致我們能夠
真的有充實的生命
去完成主給我們
在地上的使命
要求主
改變我們的心
以致我們的心能夠更加像
基督耶穌在我們的心